<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ipums-ddi-xslt.xsl"?>
<codeBook xmlns="ddi:codebook:2_5" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="ddi:codebook:2_5 http://www.ddialliance.org/Specification/DDI-Codebook/2.5/XMLSchema/codebook.xsd" version="2.5" ID="ddi2-156535_cps_00020.dat-cps.ipums.org">
  <docDscr>
    <citation>
      <titlStmt>
        <titl>Codebook for an IPUMS-CPS Data Extract</titl>
        <subTitl>DDI 2.5 metadata describing the extract file  'cps_00020.dat'</subTitl>
        <IDNo>ddi2-156535_cps_00020.dat-cps.ipums.org</IDNo>
      </titlStmt>
      <rspStmt>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Minnesota">Minnesota Population Center</AuthEnty>
      </rspStmt>
      <prodStmt>
        <producer abbr="MPC" affiliation="University of Minnesota" role="Documentation">Minnesota Population Center</producer>
        <prodDate date="2020-06-07">June 7, 2020</prodDate>
        <prodPlac>Minnesota Population Center, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</prodPlac>
      </prodStmt>
      <distStmt>
        <contact affiliation="University of Minnesota" URI="http://pop.umn.edu">Minnesota Population Center</contact>
      </distStmt>
    </citation>
  </docDscr>
  <stdyDscr>
    <citation>
      <titlStmt>
        <titl>User Extract cps_00020.dat</titl>
      </titlStmt>
      <rspStmt>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Minnesota">Minnesota Population Center</AuthEnty>
      </rspStmt>
      <prodStmt>
        <producer abbr="MPC" affiliation="University of Minnesota" role="Documentation">Minnesota Population Center</producer>
        <prodDate date="2020-06-07">June 7, 2020</prodDate>
        <prodPlac>Minnesota Population Center, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</prodPlac>
      </prodStmt>
      <distStmt>
        <contact affiliation="University of Minnesota" URI="http://pop.umn.edu">Minnesota Population Center</contact>
      </distStmt>
      <serStmt>
        <serName abbr="cps">IPUMS CPS</serName>
        <serInfo>DOI:10.18128/D030.V7.0</serInfo>
      </serStmt>
      <verStmt>
        <version date="2020-06-07"/>
      </verStmt>
    </citation>
    <stdyInfo>
      <subject>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Linking Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Linking Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Tax Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
      </subject>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2963">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2019-03">2019-03</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, ASEC 2019; regular size
]]></notes>
    </stdyInfo>
    <dataAccs>
      <useStmt>
        <confDec required="no"><![CDATA[None]]></confDec>
        <contact affiliation="Minnesota Population Center" URI="http://cps.ipums.org/">IPUMS-CPS</contact>
        <citReq><![CDATA[Publications and research reports based on the IPUMS-CPS database must cite it appropriately. The citation should include the following:

Sarah Flood,  Miriam King,  Renae Rodgers,  Steven Ruggles and J. Robert Warren. Integrated Public Use Microdata Series, Current Population Survey: Version 7.0 [dataset]. Minneapolis, MN: IPUMS, 2020. https://doi.org/10.18128/D030.V7.0

The licensing agreement for use of IPUMS-CPS data requires that users supply us with the title and full citation for any publications, research reports, or educational materials making use of the data or documentation. Please add your citation to the IPUMS bibliography: http://bibliography.ipums.org/]]></citReq>
        <conditions><![CDATA[Users of IPUMS-CPS data must agree to abide by the conditions of use. A user's license is valid for one year and may be renewed.  Users must agree to the following conditions:

(1) No fees may be charged for use or distribution of the data.  All persons are granted a limited license to use these data, but you may not charge a fee for the data if you distribute it to others.

(2) Cite IPUMS appropriately.  For information on proper citation,  refer to the citation requirement section of this DDI document.

(3) Tell us about any work you do using the IPUMS.  Publications, research  reports, or presentations making use of IPUMS-CPS should be added to our  Bibliography. Continued funding for the IPUMS depends on our ability to  show our sponsor agencies that researchers are using the data for productive  purposes.

(4) Use it for GOOD -- never for EVIL.]]></conditions>
        <disclaimer>The user of the data acknowledges that the original collector of the data, the authorized distributor of the data, and the relevant funding agency bear no responsibility for use of the data or for interpretations or inferences based upon such uses.</disclaimer>
      </useStmt>
    </dataAccs>
    <notes><![CDATA[User-provided description:  ASEC 2019]]></notes>
    <notes>This extract is a revision of the user's previous extract, number 18.</notes>
  </stdyDscr>
  <fileDscr ID="ExtractData">
    <fileTxt>
      <fileName>cps_00020.dat</fileName>
      <fileCont>Microdata records</fileCont>
      <fileStrc type="rectangular">
      </fileStrc>
      <fileType charset="ISO-8859-1">ISO-8859-1 data file</fileType>
      <format>fixed length fields</format>
      <filePlac>Minnesota Population Center, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</filePlac>
    </fileTxt>
  </fileDscr>
  <dataDscr>
    <var ID="YEAR" files="ExtractData" name="YEAR" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="1" width="4" EndPos="4"/>
      <labl>Survey year</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[YEAR reports the year in which the survey was conducted.  YEARP is repeated on person records.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
YEAR is a 4-digit numeric value.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="SERIAL" files="ExtractData" name="SERIAL" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="5" width="5" EndPos="9"/>
      <labl>Household serial number</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[SERIAL is an identifying number unique to each household in a given survey month and year.  All person records are assigned the same serial number as the household record they follow.  A combination of YEAR, MONTH, and SERIAL provides a within-sample unique identifier for every household in IPUMS-CPS; YEAR, SERIAL, and PERNUM uniquely identify every person in the database within sample.

SERIAL is a new value generated for IPUMS-CPS and should not be confused with the household serial number created by the Census Bureau and included in the original CPS data.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
SERIAL is a 5-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="MONTH" files="ExtractData" name="MONTH" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="10" width="2" EndPos="11"/>
      <labl>Month</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[MONTH indicates the calendar month of the CPS interview.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>01</catValu>
        <labl>January</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>02</catValu>
        <labl>February</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>03</catValu>
        <labl>March</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>04</catValu>
        <labl>April</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>05</catValu>
        <labl>May</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>06</catValu>
        <labl>June</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>07</catValu>
        <labl>July</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>08</catValu>
        <labl>August</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>09</catValu>
        <labl>September</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>10</catValu>
        <labl>October</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>11</catValu>
        <labl>November</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>12</catValu>
        <labl>December</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="CPSID" files="ExtractData" name="CPSID" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="12" width="14" EndPos="25"/>
      <labl>CPSID, household record</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[CPSID is an IPUMS-CPS defined variable that uniquely identifies households across CPS samples. The first six digits of CPSID index the four-digit year and two-digit month that the household was first in the CPS. CPSID allows users to link a household record across samples, based on the 4-8-4 rotation pattern, by assigning a unique CPSID value based on a combination of household identifiers. CPSID will only ever appear for a maximum of 8 times, which is the number of times a household may be observed in the CPS survey (as indexed by MIS). In some cases, a household will appear fewer than 8 times due to migration, mortality, non-response, and recording errors. CPSID Extensive documentation about the creation of CPSID is available elsewhere [URL omitted from DDI.].

CPSID may also be used to link ASEC respondents who are in the March Basic Monthly file to other months of CPS data. This linking is made possible by IPUMS through the creation of MARBASECIDP. Users should note that ASEC oversample households (as indicated by ASECOVERH) will always have a CPSID value of 0.

Users may also want to see CPSIDP for more information about linking individuals across time using a person-specific version of CPSID.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
CPSID is a 14-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Linking Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="ASECFLAG" files="ExtractData" name="ASECFLAG" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="26" width="1" EndPos="26"/>
      <labl>Flag for ASEC</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[ASECFLAG indicates whether the respondent is part of the ASEC or the March Basic. This variable is useful for users who wish to distinguish ASEC and March Basic files in their extracts. See further information [URL omitted from DDI.] about the ASEC versus the March Basic Monthly Files.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1</catValu>
        <labl>ASEC</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>2</catValu>
        <labl>March Basic</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="ASECWTH" files="ExtractData" name="ASECWTH" intrvl="contin" dcml="4">
      <location StartPos="27" width="10" EndPos="36"/>
      <labl>Annual Social and Economic Supplement Household weight</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[ASECWTH is a household-level weight that should be used to generate statistics about households in March Annual Social and Economic (ASEC) Supplement data. The CPS uses a complex stratified sampling scheme, and ASECWTH must be used to produce unbiased household-level statistics from the IPUMS-CPS ASEC data. For analyses of non-ASEC data, researchers should use HWTFINL. For individual-level analyses, researchers should use WTFINL,  ASECWT, or EARNWT. 

ASECWTH generally has the same value as WTSUPP for the household head or reference person. Vacant housing units and households that could not be interviewed due to residents' absence or refusal to participate have a value of zero in HWTSUPP; such sampled units were included in the public use CPS data beginning in 1988. 

Estimates on the entire population are prepared by projecting forward the resident population from the last available census. These projections are derived by updating the demographic census data from a number of other data sources that account for death, births and net migration. About 3 years after every census (i.e. 2003 for the 2000 Census and 2013 for the 2010 Census), the Census Bureau updates its independent population control and provides a new weight for the relevant years.

Two important points should be noted here. First, the lag between when the Census is conducted and when the CPS weights are updated is about 3 years. While the Census data are being processed, the CPS files are made available using the weighting scheme from the US Census prior to the latest Census. Second, once the files are updated, the old weights become obsolete and are replaced in the IPUMS data extract system. Published estimates from the lag years that use the old weights are not always updated. For example, 2010 poverty estimates were released in ASEC using the 2000 population controls. Once the 2010 population controls were made available, IPUMS-CPS replaced the ASEC 2010, 2011, and 2012 weights that are based on the 2000 population control with weights that are based on the 2010 population controls.

IPUMS-CPS makes available only the most up-to-date weights. The old values are available here: Old SPM and Weights Values [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
ASECWTH is a 10-digit numeric variable with four implied decimals.  That is, 1234567890 should be interpreted as 123456.7890.  The IPUMS command files automatically divide ASECWTH by 10,000, so no further adjustment is needed.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="PERNUM" files="ExtractData" name="PERNUM" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="37" width="2" EndPos="38"/>
      <labl>Person number in sample unit</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[PERNUM numbers all persons within each household consecutively (starting with "1") in the order in which they are listed in the original CPS data.  When combined with YEAR , MONTH, and SERIAL, PERNUM uniquely identifies each person within IPUMS-CPS samples, though not across IPUMS-CPS samples.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
PERNUM is a 2-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="CPSIDP" files="ExtractData" name="CPSIDP" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="39" width="14" EndPos="52"/>
      <labl>CPSID, person record</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[CPSIDP is an IPUMS-CPS defined variable that uniquely identifies individuals across CPS samples. The first six digits of CPSIDP index the four-digit year and two-digit month that the household was first in the CPS. CPSIDP allows users to link a respondent appearing with a designated household roster line number (LINENO) across samples, based on the 4-8-4 rotation pattern, by assigning a unique CPSIDP value to this line number. CPSIDP will only ever appear for a maximum of 8 times, which is the number of times a household may be observed in the CPS survey (as indexed by MISH). In some cases, individuals will appear fewer than 8 times due to migration, mortality, non-response, and recording errors. Extensive documentation about the creation of CPSIDP is available elsewhere [URL omitted from DDI.].

Users should note that it is important to verify CPSIDP linkages with AGE, SEX, and RACE. In some cases CPSIDP will result in erroneous links, which are due to errors in the source data. Cases with the same CPSIDP value may also have inconsistent responses across samples due to errors on the part of the respondent or in recording the response. Ultimately, it is up to the individual researcher to determine the acceptability of the linkages made using CPSIDP. 

CPSIDP may also be used to link ASEC respondents who are in the March Basic Monthly file to other months of CPS data. This linking is made possible by IPUMS through the creation of MARBASECIDP. 

To get started using CPSIDP, users may want to sort their data file by CPSIDP and MISH to create a person-time file. 

Users should take care when including the March Basic or ASEC as part of their linking. Respondents who are part of the ASEC oversample (as indicated by ASECOVERP) have a CPSIDP value of 0. For further information about the relationship between the March Basic and the ASEC, please see our additional documentation [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
CPSIDP is a 14-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Linking Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="ASECWT" files="ExtractData" name="ASECWT" intrvl="contin" dcml="4">
      <location StartPos="53" width="10" EndPos="62"/>
      <labl>Annual Social and Economic Supplement Weight</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[ASECWT is a person-level weight that should be used in analyses of individual-level CPS supplement data. Since the CPS relies on a complex stratified sampling scheme, it is essential to use one of the provided weighting variables.

Researchers should use WTFINL rather than ASECWT when they wish to conduct person-level analyses of non-ASEC data. EARNWT should be used for any analysis including a small number of person-level variables (EARNWEEK, HOURWAGE, PAIDHOUR, and UNION). Researchers should use  ASECWTH for household-level analyses.

User Caution: For analyses that include the 2014 ASEC sample, please see the comparability tab.

The ASEC CPS files include two groups of people who are not included in the production of published labor force statistics: (1) members of the armed services, and (2) members of the Hispanic oversample who were interviewed in months other than March. WTFINL and EARNWT assign these groups a value of 0. Both groups are assigned non-zero values in ASECWT.

ASECWT is based on the inverse probability of selection into the sample and adjustments for the following factors: failure to obtain an interview; sampling within large sample units; the known distribution of the entire population according to age, sex, and race; over-sampling Hispanic persons; to give husbands and wives the same weight; and an additional step to provide consistency with labor force estimates from the basic survey. 

Estimates on the entire population are prepared by projecting forward the resident population from the last available census. These projections are derived by updating the demographic census data from a number of other data sources that account for death, births and net migration. About 3 years after every census (i.e. 2003 for the 2000 Census and 2013 for the 2010 Census), the Census Bureau updates its independent population control and provides a new weight for the relevant years.

Two important points should be noted here. First, the lag between when the Census is conducted and when the CPS weights are updated is about 3 years. While the Census data are being processed, the CPS files are made available using the weighting scheme from the US Census prior to the latest Census. Second, once the files are updated, the old weights become obsolete and are replaced in the IPUMS data extract system. Published estimates from the lag years that use the old weights are not always updated. For example, 2010 poverty estimates were released in ASEC using the 2000 population controls. Once the 2010 population controls were made available, IPUMS-CPS replaced the ASEC 2010, 2011, and 2012 weights that are based on the 2000 population control with weights that are based on the 2010 population controls. IPUMS-CPS makes available only the most up-to-date weights.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
ASECWT is a 10-digit numeric variable with four implied decimal places. That is, values of 0012345600 should be interpreted as 1,234.56.  The IPUMS command files automatically divide ASECWT by 10,000, so no further adjustment is needed.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="OCCLY" files="ExtractData" name="OCCLY" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="63" width="4" EndPos="66"/>
      <labl>Occupation last year</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[OCCLY reports the person's primary occupation during the previous calendar year.  A respondent who held more than one job during the preceding year was to report the job that lasted longest. The reference period for OCCLY, the preceding calendar year, is the same as the reference period for income variables in IPUMS-CPS.

The CPS interviewer collected information by asking what kind of work the person was doing during the preceding calendar year, and Census Bureau staff coded the information into the CPS or census occupational classification. Researchers who wish to work with a consistent occupational coding scheme for 1968 forward should use the OCC50LY variable.  

The occupation of persons employed at the time of the survey is reported in OCC.  OCC also provides information about the most recent job for persons not in the labor force at the time of the survey.  For general discussion of employment concepts, including the definition of those not in the labor force, see the documentation on EMPSTAT.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
OCCLY is a 3-digit numeric variable for 1962-2002 and a 4-digit numeric variable for 2003 and on. Codes are the same as those for OCC, except in 1962-1967. 

1962-1967 OCCLY codes [URL omitted from DDI.]  
1968-1970 OCC and OCCLY codes [URL omitted from DDI.]  
1971-1982 OCC and OCCLY codes [URL omitted from DDI.]  
1983-1991 OCC and OCCLY codes [URL omitted from DDI.]  
1992-2002 OCC and OCCLY codes [URL omitted from DDI.]  
2003-2010 OCC and OCCLY codes  [URL omitted from DDI.]]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="CLASSWLY" files="ExtractData" name="CLASSWLY" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="67" width="2" EndPos="68"/>
      <labl>Class of worker last year</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[CLASSWLY specifies whether a person who worked during the previous calendar year was self-employed, an employee in private industry or the public sector, in the armed forces, or worked without pay in a family business or farm.  Respondents were classified by the job that they held for the longest time during the previous year.  More specific information about an individual's job during this period is given in OCCLY, OCC50LY, INDLY, and IND50LY.  

CLASSWKR relates to the respondent's job during the previous week, rather than the previous year.  CLASSWKR also reports the most recent job for respondents who were not employed in the week prior to the survey.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>29</catValu>
        <labl>Unpaid family worker</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>99</catValu>
        <labl>Missing/Unknown</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>28</catValu>
        <labl>Local government employee</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>27</catValu>
        <labl>State government employee</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>25</catValu>
        <labl>Federal government employee</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>24</catValu>
        <labl>Wage/salary, government</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>00</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>10</catValu>
        <labl>Self-employed</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>13</catValu>
        <labl>Self-employed, not incorporated</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>14</catValu>
        <labl>Self-employed, incorporated</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>22</catValu>
        <labl>Wage/salary, private</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>20</catValu>
        <labl>Works for wages or salary</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="WORKLY" files="ExtractData" name="WORKLY" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="69" width="2" EndPos="70"/>
      <labl>Worked last year</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[WORKLY indicates whether or not the respondent worked any time in the calendar year previous to the survey year.  For example, if the respondent is interviewed in March of 2015, they are reporting whether they had worked any time in 2014.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>00</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>01</catValu>
        <labl>No</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>02</catValu>
        <labl>Yes</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="FTOTVAL" files="ExtractData" name="FTOTVAL" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="71" width="10" EndPos="80"/>
      <labl>Total family income</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[FTOTVAL reports the total income for the respondent's family. Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer (i.e., in the survey year's dollar amounts). Users may want to adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
Note: Values are as they appear in the original CPS data. Top-codes, bottom-codes, and NIU codes have not been harmonized by the IPUMS.

1968-1975
50000 = Top Code (50,000 and greater)
999999 = NIU 

Values in all years can be negative.


See User Note [URL omitted from DDI.] for an explanation of these codes.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCTOT" files="ExtractData" name="INCTOT" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="81" width="9" EndPos="89"/>
      <labl>Total personal income</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCTOT indicates each respondent's total pre-tax personal income or losses from all sources for the previous calendar year.  Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
999999999 = N.I.U.
999999998 = Missing. (1962-1964 only)
Values can be negative.

The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCWAGE" files="ExtractData" name="INCWAGE" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="90" width="8" EndPos="97"/>
      <labl>Wage and salary income</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCWAGE indicates each respondent's total pre-tax wage and salary income--that is, money received as an employee--for the previous calendar year.  Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors. 

For ASEC samples 1988-onward, INCWAGE is derived from a Census recode variable.  The topcoded components of INCWAGE are OINCWAGE and INCLONGJ.  OINCWAGE  is always a component of INCWAGE.  When SRCEARN indicates that INCLONGJ is earned from wage and salary, INCLONGJ is an additional component of INCWAGE.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
99999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe)
99999998 = Missing (1962-1964 only)

The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCLONGJ" files="ExtractData" name="INCLONGJ" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="98" width="8" EndPos="105"/>
      <labl>Earnings from longest job</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCLONGJ reports the net amount (prior to deductions) that the respondent earned from the job held for the longest time during the preceding calendar year.  Whether such income derived from wages or salary or from self-employment in a business or farm is specified in SRCEARN.

Most income variables included in IPUMS-CPS report the total amount earned from a specific source (e.g., wages and salary) during the preceding calendar year.  INCLONGJ, by contrast, does not necessarily include income earned during the entire calendar year.  Imagine that an individual worked at one job for eight months, earning $10,000 in wages, and then worked for four months at two different jobs, earning an additional $5000 in wages.  Wages from the longest-held job (in this case, $10,000) would be reported in INCLONGJ.  Wage and salary income from the two jobs other than the longest-held job (in this case, $5,000) would be reported in OINCWAGE. Total earnings from wages for this person (in this case, $15,000, accrued in three different jobs) would be reported in INCWAGE.  If, however, a wage-earner worked at a single job during the preceding calendar year, the amounts reported in INCLONGJ and INCWAGE would be the same. 

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors. 

Values may be negative.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
99999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).

The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="OINCBUS" files="ExtractData" name="OINCBUS" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="106" width="7" EndPos="112"/>
      <labl>Earnings from other work included business self-employment earnings</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[OINCBUS reports net earnings from self-employment in a non-farm business, if this self-employment did not constitute the respondent's longest-held job during the previous calendar year.  The amount earned (in wages, salary, or earnings from self-employment in a business or farm) from the longest-held job during the preceding calendar year is reported in INCLONGJ.     

Imagine that a self-employed individual worked in one non-farm own business for eight months, netting $10,000 in earnings, and worked in two other non-farm own businesses for the remaining 4 months, netting an additional $12,000 in earnings.  The $12,000 in "other" net self-employment earnings (from work outside the person's primary, or longest-held, job) would be reported in OINCBUS; the $10,000 in net earnings from the individual's longest-held job would be reported in INCLONGJ; and the total amount of net self-employed non-farm business earnings from the previous calendar year ($22,000) would be reported in INCBUS.  

Imagine, instead, that as reported in SRCEARN, an individual worked as an employee earning wages for the primary job, but earned additional income working part of the year in their own non-farm businesses.  In such a case, wage income from the primary job would be reported in INCLONGJ; all self-employed non-farm net business earnings would be reported in OINCBUS; and the value of OINCBUS and INCBUS would be the same.   

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
9999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="OINCFARM" files="ExtractData" name="OINCFARM" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="113" width="8" EndPos="120"/>
      <labl>Earnings from other work included farm self-employment earnings</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[OINCFARM reports net earnings as a tenant farmer, sharecropper, or operator of one's own farm during the previous calendar year, if such work did not constitute the longest-held job during that period.  The amount earned (in wages, salary, or earnings from self-employment in a business or farm) from the longest-held job during the preceding calendar year is reported in INCLONGJ.     

Imagine that an individual considered raising crops on her own land to be her primary job, and considered money earned by harvesting crops on another farmer's land for a few days, using her own equipment, to be a secondary "own farm" job.  In such a case, net earnings from the sale of  her own crops would be reported as income in INCLONGJ; earnings from harvesting crops for another farmer would be reported as "other" self-employed own farm income in OINCFARM; and the sum of earnings from crop sales and farm equipment rental would constitute INCFARM.  If, instead, she grouped together all net earnings from crop sales and income generated from the use of her equipment into a single "own farm" business, all of this net farm income would be reported in both INCLONGJ and INCFARM, and the value of OINCFARM would be zero.  

Imagine, instead, that as reported in SRCEARN, an individual worked as an employee earning wages for the primary job, but earned additional income working part of the year on their own farm.  In such a case, wage income from the primary job would be reported in INCLONGJ; all self-employed farm net business earnings would be reported in OINCFARM; and the value of OINCFARM and INCFARM would be the same.   

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
99999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="OINCWAGE" files="ExtractData" name="OINCWAGE" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="121" width="8" EndPos="128"/>
      <labl>Earnings from other work included wage and salary earnings</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[OINCWAGE reports the net amount (prior to deductions) that the respondent earned in wages and salary, other than the amount earned in the primary (longest-held) job, during the preceding calendar year.  The amount earned (in wages, salary, or earnings from self-employment in a business or farm) from the longest held job during the preceding calendar year is reported in INCLONGJ.

Imagine that an individual worked at one job for 8 months, earning $10,000 in wages, and worked at two other jobs for the remaining 4 months, earning $12,000 in wages.  The $12,000 in "other" wage and salary earnings (wages and salary from jobs other than the person's primary, or longest-held, job) would be reported in OINCWAGE; the $10,000 in wages from the individual's longest-held job would be reported in INCLONGJ; and the total amount of wage and salary income from the previous calendar year ($22,000) would be reported in INCWAGE.

Imagine, instead, that as reported in SRCEARN, an individual was self-employed in a business or farm for their primary job, and also worked one or more additional jobs for wages. In such a case, self-employment income from the primary job would be reported in INCLONGJ; all wage and salary earnings would be reported in OINCWAGE, and the value of OINCWAGE and INCWAGE would be the same.  

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
99999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).

The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="EITCRED" files="ExtractData" name="EITCRED" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="129" width="4" EndPos="132"/>
      <labl>Earned income tax credit</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[EITCRED represents the value of the Earned Income Tax Credit for an individual or couple filing a federal income tax return. The federal Earned Income Tax Credit (EITC) is a refundable tax credit that reduces or eliminates the amount of income tax that low-to moderate-income working people are required to pay, and it frequently operates as a wage subsidy for low-income workers.  If the amount of the credit exceeds the amount owed in federal income taxes, the difference is received as a cash payment. The value of the EITC depends on the amount of earned income and family size (e.g., whether a single-parent or two-parent family and number of dependent children).

EITCRED, like other tax-related variables included in the ASEC CPS (ADJGINC, CAPGAIN, CAPLOSS, FEDRETIR, FEDTAX, FICA, FILESTAT, MARGTAX, STATETAX, and TAXINC) was not determined by direct questioning of respondents.  Rather, values for these variables come from the Census Bureau's tax model, which simulates individual tax returns to produce estimates of federal, state, and payroll taxes.  The model incorporates information from non-CPS sources, such as the Internal Revenue Service's Statistics of Income series, the American Housing Survey, and the State Tax Handbook.  For more information about the model, see Current Population Reports, Series P60-186RD.  The IPUMS-CPS staff welcomes further information from users about the interpretation of this variable or other tax-related variables in the ASEC CPS.

Amounts for EITCRED are expressed in dollars of the given year, rather than in constant dollars adjusted for inflation.  Users can adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
9999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).

See User Note [URL omitted from DDI.] for an explanation of these codes.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Tax Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
  </dataDscr>
</codeBook>
