<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ipums-ddi-xslt.xsl"?>
<codeBook xmlns="ddi:codebook:2_5" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="ddi:codebook:2_5 http://www.ddialliance.org/Specification/DDI-Codebook/2.5/XMLSchema/codebook.xsd" version="2.5" ID="ddi2-156535_cps_00019.dat-cps.ipums.org">
  <docDscr>
    <citation>
      <titlStmt>
        <titl>Codebook for an IPUMS-CPS Data Extract</titl>
        <subTitl>DDI 2.5 metadata describing the extract file  'cps_00019.dat'</subTitl>
        <IDNo>ddi2-156535_cps_00019.dat-cps.ipums.org</IDNo>
      </titlStmt>
      <rspStmt>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Minnesota">Minnesota Population Center</AuthEnty>
      </rspStmt>
      <prodStmt>
        <producer abbr="MPC" affiliation="University of Minnesota" role="Documentation">Minnesota Population Center</producer>
        <prodDate date="2020-06-07">June 7, 2020</prodDate>
        <prodPlac>Minnesota Population Center, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</prodPlac>
      </prodStmt>
      <distStmt>
        <contact affiliation="University of Minnesota" URI="http://pop.umn.edu">Minnesota Population Center</contact>
      </distStmt>
    </citation>
  </docDscr>
  <stdyDscr>
    <citation>
      <titlStmt>
        <titl>User Extract cps_00019.dat</titl>
      </titlStmt>
      <rspStmt>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Minnesota">Minnesota Population Center</AuthEnty>
      </rspStmt>
      <prodStmt>
        <producer abbr="MPC" affiliation="University of Minnesota" role="Documentation">Minnesota Population Center</producer>
        <prodDate date="2020-06-07">June 7, 2020</prodDate>
        <prodPlac>Minnesota Population Center, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</prodPlac>
      </prodStmt>
      <distStmt>
        <contact affiliation="University of Minnesota" URI="http://pop.umn.edu">Minnesota Population Center</contact>
      </distStmt>
      <serStmt>
        <serName abbr="cps">IPUMS CPS</serName>
        <serInfo>DOI:10.18128/D030.V7.0</serInfo>
      </serStmt>
      <verStmt>
        <version date="2020-06-07"/>
      </verStmt>
    </citation>
    <stdyInfo>
      <subject>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Linking Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Linking Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Outgoing Rotation Groups (Earner Study) Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
      </subject>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2969">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2020-01">2020-01</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2970">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2020-02">2020-02</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2971">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2020-03">2020-03</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2972">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2020-04">2020-04</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, January 2020; regular size
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, February 2020; regular size
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, March 2020; regular size
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, April 2020; regular size
]]></notes>
    </stdyInfo>
    <dataAccs>
      <useStmt>
        <confDec required="no"><![CDATA[None]]></confDec>
        <contact affiliation="Minnesota Population Center" URI="http://cps.ipums.org/">IPUMS-CPS</contact>
        <citReq><![CDATA[Publications and research reports based on the IPUMS-CPS database must cite it appropriately. The citation should include the following:

Sarah Flood,  Miriam King,  Renae Rodgers,  Steven Ruggles and J. Robert Warren. Integrated Public Use Microdata Series, Current Population Survey: Version 7.0 [dataset]. Minneapolis, MN: IPUMS, 2020. https://doi.org/10.18128/D030.V7.0

The licensing agreement for use of IPUMS-CPS data requires that users supply us with the title and full citation for any publications, research reports, or educational materials making use of the data or documentation. Please add your citation to the IPUMS bibliography: http://bibliography.ipums.org/]]></citReq>
        <conditions><![CDATA[Users of IPUMS-CPS data must agree to abide by the conditions of use. A user's license is valid for one year and may be renewed.  Users must agree to the following conditions:

(1) No fees may be charged for use or distribution of the data.  All persons are granted a limited license to use these data, but you may not charge a fee for the data if you distribute it to others.

(2) Cite IPUMS appropriately.  For information on proper citation,  refer to the citation requirement section of this DDI document.

(3) Tell us about any work you do using the IPUMS.  Publications, research  reports, or presentations making use of IPUMS-CPS should be added to our  Bibliography. Continued funding for the IPUMS depends on our ability to  show our sponsor agencies that researchers are using the data for productive  purposes.

(4) Use it for GOOD -- never for EVIL.]]></conditions>
        <disclaimer>The user of the data acknowledges that the original collector of the data, the authorized distributor of the data, and the relevant funding agency bear no responsibility for use of the data or for interpretations or inferences based upon such uses.</disclaimer>
      </useStmt>
    </dataAccs>
    <notes><![CDATA[User-provided description:  Core 2020]]></notes>
    <notes>This extract is a revision of the user's previous extract, number 17.</notes>
  </stdyDscr>
  <fileDscr ID="ExtractData">
    <fileTxt>
      <fileName>cps_00019.dat</fileName>
      <fileCont>Microdata records</fileCont>
      <fileStrc type="rectangular">
      </fileStrc>
      <fileType charset="ISO-8859-1">ISO-8859-1 data file</fileType>
      <format>fixed length fields</format>
      <filePlac>Minnesota Population Center, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</filePlac>
    </fileTxt>
  </fileDscr>
  <dataDscr>
    <var ID="YEAR" files="ExtractData" name="YEAR" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="1" width="4" EndPos="4"/>
      <labl>Survey year</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[YEAR reports the year in which the survey was conducted.  YEARP is repeated on person records.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
YEAR is a 4-digit numeric value.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="SERIAL" files="ExtractData" name="SERIAL" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="5" width="5" EndPos="9"/>
      <labl>Household serial number</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[SERIAL is an identifying number unique to each household in a given survey month and year.  All person records are assigned the same serial number as the household record they follow.  A combination of YEAR, MONTH, and SERIAL provides a within-sample unique identifier for every household in IPUMS-CPS; YEAR, SERIAL, and PERNUM uniquely identify every person in the database within sample.

SERIAL is a new value generated for IPUMS-CPS and should not be confused with the household serial number created by the Census Bureau and included in the original CPS data.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
SERIAL is a 5-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="MONTH" files="ExtractData" name="MONTH" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="10" width="2" EndPos="11"/>
      <labl>Month</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[MONTH indicates the calendar month of the CPS interview.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>01</catValu>
        <labl>January</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>02</catValu>
        <labl>February</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>03</catValu>
        <labl>March</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>04</catValu>
        <labl>April</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>05</catValu>
        <labl>May</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>06</catValu>
        <labl>June</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>07</catValu>
        <labl>July</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>08</catValu>
        <labl>August</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>09</catValu>
        <labl>September</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>10</catValu>
        <labl>October</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>11</catValu>
        <labl>November</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>12</catValu>
        <labl>December</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="HWTFINL" files="ExtractData" name="HWTFINL" intrvl="contin" dcml="4">
      <location StartPos="12" width="10" EndPos="21"/>
      <labl>Household weight, Basic Monthly</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[HWTFINL is a household-level weight that should be used to generate statistics about households. The CPS uses a complex stratified sampling scheme, and HWTFINL must be used to produce unbiased household-level statistics from IPUMS-CPS basic monthly samples. For analyses of March Annual Social and Economic (ASEC) data, researchers should use HWTSUPP. For individual-level analyses, researchers should use WTFINL, WTSUPP, or EARNWT. 

HWTFINL generally has the same value as WTFINL for the household head or reference person. Vacant housing units and households that could not be interviewed due to residents' absence or refusal to participate have a value of zero in HWTFINL; such sampled units were included in the public use CPS data beginning in 1988.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
HWTFINL is a 10-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="CPSID" files="ExtractData" name="CPSID" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="22" width="14" EndPos="35"/>
      <labl>CPSID, household record</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[CPSID is an IPUMS-CPS defined variable that uniquely identifies households across CPS samples. The first six digits of CPSID index the four-digit year and two-digit month that the household was first in the CPS. CPSID allows users to link a household record across samples, based on the 4-8-4 rotation pattern, by assigning a unique CPSID value based on a combination of household identifiers. CPSID will only ever appear for a maximum of 8 times, which is the number of times a household may be observed in the CPS survey (as indexed by MIS). In some cases, a household will appear fewer than 8 times due to migration, mortality, non-response, and recording errors. CPSID Extensive documentation about the creation of CPSID is available elsewhere [URL omitted from DDI.].

CPSID may also be used to link ASEC respondents who are in the March Basic Monthly file to other months of CPS data. This linking is made possible by IPUMS through the creation of MARBASECIDP. Users should note that ASEC oversample households (as indicated by ASECOVERH) will always have a CPSID value of 0.

Users may also want to see CPSIDP for more information about linking individuals across time using a person-specific version of CPSID.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
CPSID is a 14-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Linking Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="ASECFLAG" files="ExtractData" name="ASECFLAG" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="36" width="1" EndPos="36"/>
      <labl>Flag for ASEC</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[ASECFLAG indicates whether the respondent is part of the ASEC or the March Basic. This variable is useful for users who wish to distinguish ASEC and March Basic files in their extracts. See further information [URL omitted from DDI.] about the ASEC versus the March Basic Monthly Files.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1</catValu>
        <labl>ASEC</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>2</catValu>
        <labl>March Basic</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="PERNUM" files="ExtractData" name="PERNUM" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="37" width="2" EndPos="38"/>
      <labl>Person number in sample unit</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[PERNUM numbers all persons within each household consecutively (starting with "1") in the order in which they are listed in the original CPS data.  When combined with YEAR , MONTH, and SERIAL, PERNUM uniquely identifies each person within IPUMS-CPS samples, though not across IPUMS-CPS samples.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
PERNUM is a 2-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="WTFINL" files="ExtractData" name="WTFINL" intrvl="contin" dcml="4">
      <location StartPos="39" width="14" EndPos="52"/>
      <labl>Final Basic Weight</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[WTFINL is the final person-level weight that should be used in analyses of basic monthly data. 

When analyzing ASEC data, researchers should use the person weight WTSUPP. For analyses including the variables EARNWEEK, HOURWAGE, PAIDHOUR, and UNION, researchers should use the EARNWT variable. 

WTFINL is the second stage weight in CPS (see technical documentation [URL omitted from DDI.]). It is based on the inverse probability of selection into the sample and adjustments for the following factors: failure to obtain an interview; sampling within large sample units; adjustments to the known distribution of the entire population according to stage, age, sex, race, and Hispanic ethnicity; and allotting a weight of zero to populations not sampled in other monthly surveys (i.e., persons in the Hispanic oversample and members of the armed forces in ASEC samples).]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
WTFINL is a 14-digit numeric variable with four implied decimals.  That is, 12345678901234 should be interpreted as 1234567890.1234.  The IPUMS command files automatically make the necessary adjustment, so no further adjustment is needed.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="CPSIDP" files="ExtractData" name="CPSIDP" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="53" width="14" EndPos="66"/>
      <labl>CPSID, person record</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[CPSIDP is an IPUMS-CPS defined variable that uniquely identifies individuals across CPS samples. The first six digits of CPSIDP index the four-digit year and two-digit month that the household was first in the CPS. CPSIDP allows users to link a respondent appearing with a designated household roster line number (LINENO) across samples, based on the 4-8-4 rotation pattern, by assigning a unique CPSIDP value to this line number. CPSIDP will only ever appear for a maximum of 8 times, which is the number of times a household may be observed in the CPS survey (as indexed by MISH). In some cases, individuals will appear fewer than 8 times due to migration, mortality, non-response, and recording errors. Extensive documentation about the creation of CPSIDP is available elsewhere [URL omitted from DDI.].

Users should note that it is important to verify CPSIDP linkages with AGE, SEX, and RACE. In some cases CPSIDP will result in erroneous links, which are due to errors in the source data. Cases with the same CPSIDP value may also have inconsistent responses across samples due to errors on the part of the respondent or in recording the response. Ultimately, it is up to the individual researcher to determine the acceptability of the linkages made using CPSIDP. 

CPSIDP may also be used to link ASEC respondents who are in the March Basic Monthly file to other months of CPS data. This linking is made possible by IPUMS through the creation of MARBASECIDP. 

To get started using CPSIDP, users may want to sort their data file by CPSIDP and MISH to create a person-time file. 

Users should take care when including the March Basic or ASEC as part of their linking. Respondents who are part of the ASEC oversample (as indicated by ASECOVERP) have a CPSIDP value of 0. For further information about the relationship between the March Basic and the ASEC, please see our additional documentation [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
CPSIDP is a 14-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Linking Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="EMPSTAT" files="ExtractData" name="EMPSTAT" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="67" width="2" EndPos="68"/>
      <labl>Employment status</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[EMPSTAT indicates whether persons were part of the labor force--working or seeking work--and, if so, whether they were currently unemployed.  The variable also provides information on the activity (e.g., doing housework, attending school,) or status (e.g., retired, unable to work) of persons not in the labor force, as well as limited additional information on those who are in the labor force (e.g. members of the Armed Forces, those with a job, but not at work last week).  See LABFORCE for a dichotomous variable identifying whether a person participated in the labor force.

In the CPS, individuals' employment status was determined on the basis of answers to a series of questions relating to their activities during the preceding week.  Those who reported doing any work at all for pay or profit, or working at least fifteen hours without pay in a family business or farm, were classified as "at work."  Those who did not work during the previous week but who acknowledged having a job or business from which they were temporarily absent (e.g., due to illness, vacation, bad weather, or labor dispute) were also classified as employed, under the heading "has job, not at work last week."  

Because the CPS is designed to measure unemployment in the civilian population, the original employment status variable in the survey classifies members of the armed forces as NIU (Not in universe).

Unemployed persons make up the third element of the labor force.  Individuals were coded as unemployed if they did no work for pay or profit, did not have a job from which they were briefly absent, and either reported looking for work as their major activity during the previous week (for 1962 through 1993) or answered yes to a question about whether they had been looking for work in the past four weeks.  People who were temporarily laid off from a job were also classified as unemployed.   A separate CPS variable specifying whether an unemployed person had worked before or was looking for a first job was used to distinguish between "experienced" and "inexperienced" unemployed persons in IPUMS-CPS.

Persons who were neither employed nor unemployed fall into the residual category, "not in labor force."  Such individuals might be retired, disabled due to an illness lasting at least 6 months, occupied with other activities such as attending school or keeping house, or convinced that they are unlikely to find employment (discouraged workers).]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>00</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>01</catValu>
        <labl>Armed Forces</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>10</catValu>
        <labl>At work</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>12</catValu>
        <labl>Has job, not at work last week</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>20</catValu>
        <labl>Unemployed</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>21</catValu>
        <labl>Unemployed, experienced worker</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>22</catValu>
        <labl>Unemployed, new worker</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>30</catValu>
        <labl>Not in labor force</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>31</catValu>
        <labl>NILF, housework</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>32</catValu>
        <labl>NILF, unable to work</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>33</catValu>
        <labl>NILF, school</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>34</catValu>
        <labl>NILF, other</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>35</catValu>
        <labl>NILF, unpaid, lt 15 hours</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>36</catValu>
        <labl>NILF, retired</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="LABFORCE" files="ExtractData" name="LABFORCE" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="69" width="1" EndPos="69"/>
      <labl>Labor force status</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[LABFORCE is a dichotomous variable indicating whether the respondent participated in the labor force during the preceding week.  See EMPSTAT for a more detailed employment status variable.   Those coded as "yes" in LABFORCE were either: were at work; held a job but were temporarily absent from work due to factors like vacation or illness; were seeking work; or were temporarily laid off from a job during the reference period.  

Because the CPS is designed to measure unemployment in the civilian population, the original dichotomous employment status variable in the survey classifies members of the armed forces as NIU (Not in universe).]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>2</catValu>
        <labl>Yes, in the labor force</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1</catValu>
        <labl>No, not in the labor force</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>0</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="OCC" files="ExtractData" name="OCC" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="70" width="4" EndPos="73"/>
      <labl>Occupation</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[OCC reports the person's primary occupation.  Respondents who held more than one job were to report the job at which they worked the largest number of hours.  For persons who were employed at the time of the survey, OCC relates to the job worked during the preceding week; unemployed persons and those not currently in the labor force were to give their most recent occupation.   The CPS interviewer collected information by asking what kind of work the person was doing, and Census Bureau staff coded the information into the contemporary CPS or census occupational classification.  Researchers who wish to work with a consistent occupational coding scheme for 1968 forward should use the OCC1950 variable.  For general discussion of employment concepts, including the definition of those not in the labor force, see the documentation on EMPSTAT.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
OCC is a 4-digit numeric variable.
(Codes for 1962-1967 are 2 digits; each is preceded by two zeros).
(Codes for 1968-2002 are 3 digits; each is preceded by a zero in the first position.)

1962-1967 [URL omitted from DDI.]  
1968-1970 [URL omitted from DDI.]
1971-1982 [URL omitted from DDI.]
1983-1991 [URL omitted from DDI.]
1992-2002 [URL omitted from DDI.]
2003-2010 [URL omitted from DDI.]
2011-2019 [URL omitted from DDI.]
2020+ [URL omitted from DDI.]]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="CLASSWKR" files="ExtractData" name="CLASSWKR" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="74" width="2" EndPos="75"/>
      <labl>Class of worker</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[CLASSWKR indicates whether a respondent was self-employed, was an employee in private industry or the public sector, was in the armed forces, or worked without pay in a family business or farm.  Workers with multiple sources of employment were classified according to the job in which they worked the most hours.  For persons employed at the time of the survey, CLASSWKR relates to the respondent's job during the previous week.  Respondents who were not employed during the previous week reported the most recent job.  The CLASSWLY variable deals with the longest job held during the previous calendar year. 

In the original CPS public use data, members of the armed forces are coded as N.I.U. (Not in Universe), because they are not part of the civilian labor force.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>00</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>10</catValu>
        <labl>Self-employed</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>13</catValu>
        <labl>Self-employed, not incorporated</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>14</catValu>
        <labl>Self-employed, incorporated</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>20</catValu>
        <labl>Works for wages or salary</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>21</catValu>
        <labl>Wage/salary, private</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>22</catValu>
        <labl>Private, for profit</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>23</catValu>
        <labl>Private, nonprofit</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>24</catValu>
        <labl>Wage/salary, government</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>25</catValu>
        <labl>Federal government employee</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>26</catValu>
        <labl>Armed forces</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>27</catValu>
        <labl>State government employee</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>28</catValu>
        <labl>Local government employee</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>29</catValu>
        <labl>Unpaid family worker</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>99</catValu>
        <labl>Missing/Unknown</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="UHRSWORKT" files="ExtractData" name="UHRSWORKT" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="76" width="3" EndPos="78"/>
      <labl>Hours usually worked per week at all jobs</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[UHRSWORKT is the usual number of hours per week the respondent reports being at all jobs, over an unspecified time period.

See the Hours Worked Variables Notes [URL omitted from DDI.] for an overview of the different actual and usual hours worked variables available.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>997</catValu>
        <labl>Hours vary</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>999</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="UHRSWORK1" files="ExtractData" name="UHRSWORK1" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="79" width="3" EndPos="81"/>
      <labl>Hours usually worked per week at main job</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[UHRSWORK1 is the usual number of hours per week the respondent reports being at their main job. There is no time period specified, unlike for UHRSWORKLY, which specifies the reference time period as last year. 

See the Hours Worked Variables Notes [URL omitted from DDI.] for an overview of the different actual and usual hours worked variables available.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>997</catValu>
        <labl>Hours vary</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>999</catValu>
        <labl>NIU/Missing</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>000</catValu>
        <labl>0 hours</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="UHRSWORK2" files="ExtractData" name="UHRSWORK2" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="82" width="3" EndPos="84"/>
      <labl>Hours usually worked per week, other job(s)</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[UHRSWORK2 is the usual number of hours per week the respondent reports being at any other job(s) besides their main job. For usual hours reported at their main job, see UHRSWORK1. There is no time period specified, unlike for UHRSWORKLY, which specifies the time period to be last year. 

See the Hours Worked Variables Notes [URL omitted from DDI.] for an overview of the different actual and usual hours worked variables available.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>999</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>998</catValu>
        <labl>Missing</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>997</catValu>
        <labl>Hours vary</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="AHRSWORKT" files="ExtractData" name="AHRSWORKT" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="85" width="3" EndPos="87"/>
      <labl>Hours worked last week</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[AHRSWORKT reports the total number of hours the respondent was at work during the previous week.  For employers and the self-employed, this includes all hours spent attending to their operation(s) or enterprise(s).  For employees, it is the number of hours they spent at work.  For unpaid family workers, it is the number of hours spent doing work directly related to the family business or farm (not including housework).

See the Hours Worked Variables Notes [URL omitted from DDI.] for an overview of the different actual and usual hours worked variables.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
AHRSWORKT is a 3-digit numeric variable.

999 = NIU (Not in universe)]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="AHRSWORK1" files="ExtractData" name="AHRSWORK1" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="88" width="3" EndPos="90"/>
      <labl>Hours worked last week, main job</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[AHRSWORK1 is the actual number of hours the respondent reported working at his/her main job last week. 

See the Hours Worked Variables Notes [URL omitted from DDI.] for an overview of the different actual and usual hours worked variables available.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>999</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="AHRSWORK2" files="ExtractData" name="AHRSWORK2" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="91" width="3" EndPos="93"/>
      <labl>Hours worked last week, other job(s)</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[AHRSWORK2 is the actual number of hours the respondent reported working at jobs other than his/her main job last week. 

See the Hours Worked Variables Notes [URL omitted from DDI.] for an overview of the different actual and usual hours worked variables available.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>999</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="EARNWT" files="ExtractData" name="EARNWT" intrvl="contin" dcml="4">
      <location StartPos="94" width="10" EndPos="103"/>
      <labl>Earnings weight</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[EARNWT is a person-level weight that should be used in any analysis including one of the following variables: EARNWEEK, HOURWAGE, PAIDHOUR, UNION, UHRSWORKORG, WKSWORKORG, ELIGORG, and OTPAY. For any other analysis using ASEC data, researchers should use WTSUPP or for analyses of non-ASEC data, WTFINL.

Individuals in the 6 rotation groups that were not asked the "earner study" questions (covering EARNWEEK, HOURWAGE, PAIDHOUR, UNION, UHRSWORKORG, WKSWORKORG, ELIGORG, and OTPAY) have a value of zero for EARNWT. Even in the 2 rotation groups where "earner study" questions were fielded, members of the armed forces have a value of zero for EARNWT.  

According to Technical Paper 66 [URL omitted from DDI.], issued jointly by the Census Bureau and the Bureau of Labor Statistics, individuals eligible for the earner study are civilians age 15 and older in rotation groups 4 or 8 who are not self-employed. In the data itself, this is true in all samples up to and including those in 1997. From 1998 to 2010, only individuals age 16 and older in rotation groups 4 or 8, and are not self-employed, are in universe for this variable. This universe also applies to basic monthly samples after 2010. In ASEC samples after 2010, the data reflect the published universe.

In any given month, approximately 1/4 of the CPS sample is in the earner study and each household should appear in the earner study exactly twice. Based on documentation from Unicon and  NBER [URL omitted from DDI.], and after an inspection of the original CPS data, we recommend that users impose the CPS eligibility restrictions in any analyses of earner study variables.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
EARNWT is an 8-digit numeric variable with four implied decimals.  That is, 12345678 should be interpreted as 1234.5678.  The IPUMS command files automatically divide EARNWT by 10000, so no further adjustment is needed.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="HOURWAGE" files="ExtractData" name="HOURWAGE" intrvl="contin" dcml="2">
      <location StartPos="104" width="5" EndPos="108"/>
      <labl>Hourly wage</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[HOURWAGE reports how much the respondent earned per hour in the current job, for those workers paid an hourly wage (and coded as "2" in PAIDHOUR).  Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.  Researchers should use the EARNWT weight with this variable.

Users should note that HOURWAGE originally had two implied decimal places, but was revised so that the command files provided by IPUMS divide HOURWAGE by 100.

HOURWAGE is one of the Outgoing Rotation/Earner Study [URL omitted from DDI.] questions.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
999.99 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).

This variable is topcoded. More information on hourly wage topcoding can be found here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Outgoing Rotation Groups (Earner Study) Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="PAIDHOUR" files="ExtractData" name="PAIDHOUR" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="109" width="1" EndPos="109"/>
      <labl>Paid by the hour</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[PAIDHOUR is a dichotomous variable indicating whether the respondent was paid by the hour for their current job or not.  Researchers should use the EARNWT weight with this variable.

PAIDHOUR is one of the Outgoing Rotation/Earner Study [URL omitted from DDI.] questions.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>2</catValu>
        <labl>Yes</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>0</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1</catValu>
        <labl>No</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>6</catValu>
        <labl>Refused</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>7</catValu>
        <labl>Don't Know</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Outgoing Rotation Groups (Earner Study) Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="EARNWEEK" files="ExtractData" name="EARNWEEK" intrvl="contin" dcml="2">
      <location StartPos="110" width="8" EndPos="117"/>
      <labl>Weekly earnings</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[EARNWEEK reports how much the respondent usually earned per week at their current job, before deductions.   Interviewers asked directly about total weekly earnings and also collected information about the usual number of hours worked per week and the hourly rate of pay at the current job.  The figure given in EARNWEEK is the higher of the values derived from these two sources: 1) the respondent's answer to the question, "How much do you usually earn per week at this job before deductions?"; or 2) for workers paid by the hour (and coded as "2" in PAIDHOUR), the reported number of hours the respondent usually worked at the job, multiplied by the hourly wage rate given in HOURWAGE. 

The values in EARNWEEK are in dollars, with no implied decimal places; a value of 500 means that the respondent earned five hundred dollars per week before deductions.  Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.  Researchers should use the EARNWT weight with this variable.

EARNWEEK is one of the Outgoing Rotation/Earner Study [URL omitted from DDI.] questions.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
9999.99 = N.I.U. 

		
1982-1988: 999 (Weekly earnings of $999 or more).
1989-1997: 1923 (Weekly earnings of $1923 or more).
1998-onward: 2885 (Weekly earnings of $2885 or more: ASEC samples only). 2884.61 for non-ASEC samples.

See User Note [URL omitted from DDI.] for an explanation of these codes.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Outgoing Rotation Groups (Earner Study) Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="UHRSWORKORG" files="ExtractData" name="UHRSWORKORG" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="118" width="3" EndPos="120"/>
      <labl>Usual hours worked per week, outgoing rotation groups</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[UHRSWORKORG reports the total number of hours the respondent who is paid hourly usually works per week at their main job. UHRSWORKORG is one of the earner study/outgoing rotation group questions. Private wage or salaried workers are asked the periodicity for which they are paid. Workers who are paid by the hour, excluding those who are self-employed, are asked the hourly wage, and then are asked how many hours they usually work per week at that rate. Researchers should use the EARNWT weight with this variable.

Researchers should note that PAIDHOUR, which identifies workers paid hourly, is more inclusive than the universe for UHRSWORKORG. This stems from the fact that PAIDHOUR is the combination of two variables that assess hourly work status while usual hours worked for hourly wage earners is only asked of individuals who respond to one of the two questions that they are paid hourly. 

UHRSWORKORG differs from UHRSWORKLY because the period of reference for UHRSWORKLY is the preceding year, whereas UHRSWORKORG refers to the current usual number of hours worked per week.  Additionally, UHRSWORKORG differs from  UHRSWORK1 in that UHRSWORK1 does not have the qualifier "at this rate" in the question. Note that for basic samples 1982-1988 and ASECs 1982-1987, the outgoing rotation usual hours question wording matches that of UHRSWORK1. Thus this variable is included in UHRSWORK1   for those years, not in UHRSWORKORG. AHRSWORK1 specifically gives the number of hours worked last week at the main job, regardless of whether this was the usual number of hours worked. 

UHRSWORKORG is one of the Outgoing Rotation/Earner Study [URL omitted from DDI.] questions.

See the Hours Worked Variables Notes [URL omitted from DDI.] for an overview of the different actual and usual hours worked variables available.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
UHRSWORK is a 3-digit numeric variable.

998 = Don't Know
999 = NIU (Not In Universe)]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Outgoing Rotation Groups (Earner Study) Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="WKSWORKORG" files="ExtractData" name="WKSWORKORG" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="121" width="2" EndPos="122"/>
      <labl>Weeks worked per year, outgoing rotation groups</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[WKSWORKORG reports the number of weeks, in single weeks, that the respondent usually works per year.  WKSWORKORG is one of the earner study questions, which is also known as the outgoing rotation group questions.  Private wage or salaried workers are asked the periodicity for which they are paid.  Workers who are paid annually, excluding those who are self-employed, are asked how many weeks a year they are paid for.  Researchers should use the EARNWT weight with this variable.

WKSWORKORG differs from WKSWORK1 in that the period of reference for WKSWORK1 is the preceding year, whereas WKSWORKORG corresponds to the respondent's current usual weeks worked per year.

WKSWORKORG is one of the Outgoing Rotation/Earner Study [URL omitted from DDI.] questions.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
WKSWORKORG is a 2-digit numeric value.

0 = NIU (Not In Universe)
98 = Don't Know]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Outgoing Rotation Groups (Earner Study) Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
  </dataDscr>
</codeBook>
